A Guide to the Sheetz-Dellinger Collection, 1870-1956
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Special Collections, James Madison University
Sheetz-Dellinger Collection1870-1956
Special Collections, James Madison University
P0001
1.5 boxes, (.63 Linear ft)
The Sheetz-Dellinger Collection, 1870s-1950s, is comprised of 92 photographs, two Edinburg High School diplomas, an assortment of school report cards and other papers, and various miscellaneous materials pertaining to James S. Sheetz, Frances Dellinger Sheetz, and their family and friends.
James Sheetz and Francis Dellinger Sheetz
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Acquisition Information
Purchased on 25 August 2009.
Provenance
This collection came from the estate sale of James and Frances (Dellinger) Sheetz and subsequent re-sale on Ebay. In September of 2010 the Carrier Library purchased the collection for the James Madison University Special Collections.
Biographical Information
James Samuel Sheetz of Edinburg, Virginia, was born on 6 April 1917. He graduated from Edinburg High School in 1937 and married Francis Dellinger, also of Edinburg (date unknown). James passed away on 22 May 1994.
Frances Dellinger Sheetz was born on 23 May 1918 in Edinburg, Virginia, to Lula and John Dellinger. Frances graduated from Edinburg High School in 1937 and married James S. Sheetz of Edinburg. She was an active member of her community and church, first at St. Paul's United Church of Christ of Edinburg until its dissolution, and then to St. Johns United Church of Christ in Hamburg. She was also a participant of the Edinburg Fire Company Ladies Auxiliary, the Shenandoah County Memorial Hospital Auxiliary, the Homemakers Department of the Shenandoah County Fair Association, the Edinburg Heritage Foundation, and the Family and Community Education Club. Frances passed away on Thursday, 16 April 2009, at the age of 90.
Scope and Content
The Sheetz-Dellinger Collection, 1870s-1950s, consists of .63 linear feet of material. The bulk of the material was created between the 1880s and 1930s. Originally purchased from the Sheetz estate sale in 2009, the collection consists of two series: Photographs and Ephemera.
Series I, Photographs, contains eleven folders of portraits and other photographic images of various men, women, and children; presumably friends and family members of the Sheetz and Dellinger families. All of the photos are sepia or black and white, and most are accompanied by a matte frame which sometimes gives the photographer's name and is decoratively embellished. All of the images are arranged by subject matter, beginning with large groups, couples, families, women, men, children, and finally houses, landscapes, and miscellaneous photos. A large portion of the photographs are professionally done, and as a whole Series I offers a glimpse into the popular fashions of men, women, and children in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries.
Series II, Ephemera, is composed of three folders that include school materials such as report cards, diplomas, a book of graduation name cards, and various ceremony and theatrical programs. The last of the three folders is titled "Miscellaneous" and consists of memorial cards, election reminder and birthday cards, a newspaper clipping, a Lententide folio from Emanuel Lutheran Church, a theatrical play booklet, and a used envelope. The memorial cards may prove useful when researching death and memorial rituals of Victorian culture in the late nineteenth century.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 2 series:
The arrangement of series is as follows:
I.Photographs
a. Groups
b. Couples
c. Families
d. Women
e. Men
f. Children
g. Houses, Landscapes, and Miscellaneous
II. Ephemera
a. School Papers
b. School Ephemera
c. Miscellaneous
The collection is arranged and listed by the item level in the container list, below.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
"Obituaries: Sheetz, Frances D." Northern Virginia Daily, 18 April 2009.
"Sheetz, James S." Social Security Death Index, accessed on 7 February 2011 at http://ssdi.rootsweb.ancestry.com/cgi-bin/ssdi.cgi.
Contents List
- Photographs1870-1950, 2 boxes
  - Large Groups:, 3 images
    - Portrait of group of men and women standing on the steps of a large brick building., 01.01:
    - Photo of group of middle-aged men in front of a large white house.1900, 01.02:
    - Portrait of a group of women, men and children in front of a brick wall with a white window. Many women holding books.1800, 01.03:
  - Couples:, 7 images
    - Portrait of middle-aged couple and terrier on leash in front of a painted cloth and lace backdrop. 1885., 02.01:; Photographer: Geo W. Brown.
    - “Jim Lehew and Florence Lehew.” Portrait of young couple in front of a painted cloth backdrop. 1880., 02.02:
    - Portrait of a young couple in front of a painted backdrop. Man has complete heterochromia. 1900., 02.03:; Photographer: T.M. Hemmings, Photographic Artist, Front Royal, Virginia.
    - Oval bust portrait of a young couple. 1900., 02.04:
    - A young couple, possibly a wedding portrait. 1920., 02.05:; Photographer: The Morrison Studio, Woodstock, Virginia.
    - “Mr. and Mrs. Clarence Bouserman.” Portrait of a couple on the front of a postcard. 1915., 02.06:
    - Portrait of a couple in front of a misty background.1910., 02.07:; Photographer: The Donaldson Studio, 927 F. ST. N.W. Washington, D.C.
  - Families:, 3 images
    - Portrait of family including mother, father, female toddler, and baby.1940., 03.01:
    - Photo of family including middle-aged man and woman, two young daughters, and a terrier. Each person wearing some white linen on their bodies in the form of a mask or or other unusual use, perhaps for Halloween or some sort of gag.1910., 03.02:
    - Portrait of family including middle-aged male and female, another female and infant in front of a leafy background. 1890., 03.03:; Photographer: N. A. Harris.
  - Women:, 16 images
    - Portrait of a young woman., 04.01:
    - Portrait of two young women in front of a misty background. “For Mother” written on back; presumable sisters. Circa 1910., 04.02:
    - Very small bust portrait of a woman. Circa 1890., 04.03:
    - Three older women in coats standing outside of a porch and bushes. Circa 1950., 04.04:
    - Two older women in dresses standing outside of a porch and bushes. September 1956, 04.05:
    - Photo of an older woman in dress sitting on the steps of a porch; a man’s legs can be seen standing on the porch behind her. “Looks as tho Walter wanted to be in the picture too” written on back. Circa 1950., 04.06:
    - Portrait of a young woman on the front of a postcard. Circa 1900., 04.07:
    - Portrait of a girl. Circa 1900., 04.08:; Photographer: C.H. Beazley, Edinburg, Virginia.
    - Portrait of a woman smiling brightly. Circa 1950., 04.09:
    - Photo of a young girl standing in front of a closed board fence in a grassless yard. Circa 1900., 04.10:
    - Portrait of a young woman wearing a fur scarf and muff. Circa 1910., 04.11:; Photographer: A. L. Wortley, Moughton, Mich(igan).
    - Portrait of a young woman with bobbed hair in front of a misty background. Circa 1925., 04.12:; Photograher: J.E. Casson, Washington, D.C.
    - Portrait of a young woman sitting in a carved chair in front of a lace backdrop., 04.13:
    - Oval portrait of a woman. Circa 1910., 04.14:; Photographer: Dean’s Studio, Harrisonburg, Virginia.
    - Postage-stamp portrait of a young woman. Circa 1910., 04.15:
    - “Joe.” Portrait of a woman standing in front of a painted backdrop and next to a wicker chair. Circa 1890., 04.16:; Photographer: Harper and Co.
  - Men:, 28 images
    - Oval bust portrait of a young man. Circa 1900., 05.01:; Photographer: Stanton Photo Co. Springfield, Ohio. A reprint of the original per the typescript on the back.
    - Very obscured photo of two men on a porch. Circa 1900., 05.02:
    - Photo of a man reclining on outdoors on a sleeping bag on the ground reading a book with a plate of stacked fruit next to him., 05.03:
    - Somewhat obscured photo of a man holding a horse by its bit., 05.04:
    - Portrait of a middle-aged man that is in a bronze- color metal frame., 05.05:; Photographer: Photomatic, International Mutoscope Corporation, New York City.
    - Portrait of a young man with a European castle background. Circa 1900., 05.06:
    - Portrait of a young man in front of a misty background. Circa 1900., 05.07:
    - Portrait of a young man with a misty background. Circa 1900., 05.08:
    - Portrait of an older man with a misty background. Printed on card stock with what seems to be a broadsheet of sorts. Circa 1885., 05.09:
    - “Grayson Burke.” Portrait of a young man on the front of a postcard sitting on a decorated wooden and leather chair. Circa 1900., 05.10:
    - Portrait of a young man wearing a WWII Army winter service uniform and a garrison cap on the front of a postcard. Circa 1940., 05.11:
    - “Bruce Rucker.” Portrait of a young man wearing a suit and a hat., 05.12:
    - Portrait of a man wearing a good suit and standing in a highly decorated room. Circa 1890., 05.13:; Photographer: Morrison Photographer, Harrisonburg Virginia.
    - Portrait of a man wearing a wool suit., 05.14:; Photographer: McCrary and Branson, Knoxville, Tennessee.
    - Photo of five men and one horse in an outdoor setting., 05:15
    - Bust portrait of an older man with a full beard. Circa 1890., 06.01:
    - Bust portrait of a man., 06.02:; Photographer: Holman, Park Avenue, Warren, O.
    - Portrait of a man standing in front of a cloth backdrop. Circa 1870., 06.03:
    - Portrait of a young man that is standing against a painted scene backdrop., 06.04:; Photographer: H. Morrison Jr, Court Street Studio, Woodstock, Virginia.
    - Photo of two men, each holding a horse by its bit. Circa 1890., 06.05:
    - Portrait of two men seated side by side. Circa 1900., 06.06:; More faded duplicate of 06.07.
    - Portrait of two men seated side by side. Circa 1900., 06.07:; Less faded duplicate of 06.06.
    - Photo of two men standing side by side in front of a slender tree, possibly a crepe myrtle. Circa 1910., 06.08:
    - “Ruth A. Fadley, 1904.” Photo of a young boy standing outside in front of snowy woods., 06.09:
    - Portrait of three men in two rows posed in front of a painted backdrop. Circa 1890., 06.10:
    - Photo of three men sitting in a row outside of a white house. Circa 1900., 06.11:
    - Photo of four men in two rows; two standing and two sitting on a suspended split log. Circa 1900., 06.12:
    - Oval bust portrait of a man., 06.13:
  - Children:, 33 images
    - “Makil in school.” Small photo of a young boy sitting on a bench at a table with a book open in front of him. Circa 1900., 07.01:
    - “John and Ida.” Portrait of two young children standing in front of a painted backdrop. Circa 1870., 07.02:; Photographer: W.A. Smith Photographic Art Studio, NO. 125 North Third St., Newark, Oh.
    - “For Lula A. Burke, this is Little Grayson Burke.” Portrait of a toddler in a white gown. Circa 1900., 07.03:; Photographer: Osbourn, Charlestown, West Virginia.
    - Photo of a toddler sitting on a decorated couch. Circa 1940., 07.04:
    - “Newland Girls.” Portrait of three children; two young girls and one infant, all standing on a porch. Circa 1910., 07.05:
    - “Elizabeth, from Teresa N. Photo of eight children in two rows, all sitting and standing outside in an open field with Model T cars in the background. Circa 1910., 07.06:
    - Portrait of a young, smiling girl on the front of a postcard. Girl is standing in front of a painted backdrop next to a large chair with a porcelain doll in it., 07.07:
    - Portrait of a young girl and boy on the front of a postcard. Circa 1900., 07.08:
    - “Luella, Reva, and Alan Winelle.” Photo of three young children; two girls and one boy, with the youngest sitting in a wagon in the front row. Circa 1900., 07.09:
    - Portrait of an infant wearing white cap and gown with thumb in its mouth and smiling. Circa 1910., 07.10:
    - “Jake and Zulas Kids.” Photo of three young children. Circa 1900., 08.01:
    - Portrait of an infant dressed in white and sitting against a patterned background., 08.02:
    - Portrait of an infant wearing a white gown and propped up on a white blanket. Circa 1900., 08.03:
    - Portrait of a female toddler holding a jingle bell rattle. Circa 1890., 08.04:
    - Portrait of an infant sitting among decorated pillows and blankets with a fringed white curtain in the background. Circa 1880., 08.05:; Photographer: T.M. Hemming, Photographic Artist, Front Royal, Virginia.
    - Photo of a young girl with a blanket hanging in the background. Circa 1900., 08.06:
    - Photo of a young girl standing on a porch with a small dog to her left. Circa 1900., 08.07:
    - Portrait of an infant sitting on a chair covered with fur against a painted backdrop. Circa 1890., 08.08:
    - Photo of a young boy and an infant; the boy standing and the infant sitting in fir chair on a porch. Circa 1900., 08.09:
    - Portrait of an infant wearing a white cap, gown, and, 08.10:; booties. Photographer: Donaldson Studio, 927 ST NW Washington DC
    - A portrait of a young boy with a tabby cat in his lap. Circa 1880., 09.01:
    - “Luther and Margaret Hunt.” Portrait of a young boy and female toddler in front of a painted backdrop, printed on the front of a postcard. January 2, 1920., 09.02:; Photographer: The Morrison Studio, Woodstock, Virginia.
    - Portrait of an infant on the front of a postcard. September 24, 1914., 09.03:
    - Portrait of an infant sitting on a checkered pillow against a painted backdrop. Circa 1920., 09.04:; Photographer: The Morrison Studio, Woodstock, Virginia.
    - Postcard portrait of a female toddler sitting on a polished wooden table against a painted backdrop., 09.05:; Photographer: The Morrison Studio, Woodstock, Virginia.
    - Portrait of an infant sitting on a cushioned wooden chair. Circa 1920., 09.06:; Photographer: The Morrison Studio, Woodstock, Virginia.
    - “Alva Lee Dellinger.”Postcard portrait of a young child in a sailor outfit. Circa 1900., 09.07:; Photographer: The Morrison Studio, Woodstock, Virginia.
    - Photo of a boy riding a pony. Circa 1920., 10.01:
    - “Betty Jane Steed.” Portrait of a very young girl in a white gown and white booties. November 24, 1923., 10.02:; Photographer: The Morrison Studio, Woodstock, Virginia.
    - “Baby George at 2 ½ years.” Portrait of a very young boy sitting on a wooden stool against a drapery background and holding a toy ball. Circa 1920., 10.03:; Photographer: Rockwood Studio, 510 W. 145th St. New York.
    - Portrait of a very young girl sitting on a polished wooden table against a painted backdrop and holding a compact., 10.04:; Photographer: The Morrison Studio, Woodstock, Virginia.
    - Portrait of a young girl sitting on a cushioned wooden chair. Circa 1930., 10.05:; Photographer: The Morrison Studio, Woodstock, Virginia
    - Portrait of a toddler standing on a wicker chair., 10.06:; Photographer: Seckner, Ft. Collins, Colorado.
  - Houses, Landscape, Misc.:, 2 images
    - “Aunt Ella’s Home.” Photograph of the outside of a white house and attached fence and yard, with a small dog in the forefront., 11.01:
    - Photograph of an outdoor scene that includes four women and two small children standing in the left edge of the background. Scene includes small houses, outbuildings, small stream, multiple posts, ground vines., 11.02:
- Ephemera1889-1939, 3 folders
  - School Papers
    - Report cards for Evelyn and Frances Dellinger from Edinburg Graded chool and Edinburg High School, 1926-1939 (Box-folder 2:12)
    - Certificate of Attendance for Frances Dellinger, 1933 (Box-folder 2:12)
    - Program for the senior class play, “Mr. Cinderella,” 1937 (Box-folder 2:12)
    - Program of Graduate Exercises, Edinburg High School, 1937 (Box-folder 2:12)
  - School Ephemera
    - One black, string-bound notebook embossed with title “Personal Cards from Classmates,”, contains 32 name cards on 8 full pages (Box-folder 2:13)
    - Edinburg High School Diploma of Frances Louise Dellinger, 1937 (Box-folder 2:13)
    - Edinburg High School Diploma of James Samuel Sheetz, 1937 (Box-folder 2:13)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Five cardboard memorial cards that gives the date of death for Carl W. Branham, Fred P. Branham, William Bowman, Caroline Bowers, and Mrs. Sarah Rinker, 1889-1895 (Box-folder 2:14)
    - An election reminder card endorsing Burder B. Bowman, 1905 (Box-folder 2:14)
    - Birthday card to Frances Dellinger, 1921 (Box-folder 2:14)
    - One paper-bound booklet of “The Cure-All,” a play, 1924 (Box-folder 2:14)
    - A small Lententide folio from Emanuel Lutheran Church, 1937 (Box-folder 2:14)
    - Newspaper clipping with a facial lotion recipe, undated (Box-folder 2:14)
    - One used envelope from the D.C. Heath and Co. to James Galloway in Moores Store, Virginia, undated (Box-folder 2:14)